[Music]
Stanford
University yeah all right so let's let's
just for a moment uh stop and say what
we'll do next time I'm not sure whether
tonight I will get to one of the key
puzzles which is called the gauge
hierarchy we may I had planned it in my
notes and we may get to it especially
since I'm getting rid of the um the
review uh
but next quarter I want to study some of
these paradoxes not paradoxes but
difficulties of the theory and how
things like super
symmetry relate to them how super
symmetry may or may not solve some of
these um uh puzzling features of the
theory how unification what unification
right now we have su3 we have su2 and we
have U1 I'm talking now about the forces
weak electromagnetic and uh and strong
do these somehow sit in some bigger
structure is there a group for example
which contains the subgroups su3 su2 and
U1 I haven't told you what a subgroup is
but you can
imagine um is there a bigger structure a
bigger mathematical structure that
contains su3 su2 and U1 yes there's a
subgroup there's a group called
su5 and there's a lot of interesting
evidence that this whole structure that
I've described so far fits very very
neatly into an su5 structure in which
quirks and leptons are all part of the
same
multiplets we'll talk about that super
symmetry
unification and uh the various puzzles
that
arise and I will tell you a little bit
about what l l c is cooked up to
discover all right now one thing the LHC
was cooked up originally to discover was
of course the higs
bong um the higs boson discovering the
higs boson is not just discovering the
higs boson for example last it's more
than just discovering the existence of a
particle it also involves a
whole bunch of properties of this
particle which are all related to the
fact that it is higs BOS on for example
um I told you the I think it was last
time how the higs BOS on and the hick
phenomena is related to the masses of
Fons we looked at the dra equation
instead of looking at the dur equation
we might have looked at the lran for the
dur equation I don't know if we ever
wrote down the lran for the dur
equation I don't think we did let me
write it down for you equation yeah we
did the Klein gour let me write it down
for you it's it's very easy we first
write down the dra
equation
uh derivative with respect to X mu
of uh derivative with respect to time of
s what was it minus or plus I don't
remember plus
um derivative with respect to X I where
x sub I means X Y or Z times Alpha
i s we can put the alpha I out
here and we set that equal to what beta
time the mass Right Time s that was the
direct equation let me move everything
over to the left hand
side did I ever tell you my great my
greatest mathematical discovery you
don't need you don't need the equal sign
right
right you made that Discovery too how
how old were you no you told it oh I
told you
okay okay this is the direct equation
now supposing I want to derive this
direct equation by variation with
respect to something in particular it
happens to be size stars that you vary
with respect to well there's a very easy
way of constructing a LR Ian such that
when you vary with respect to S star
it's the dur equation which falls out
all you have to do is multiply the
direct equation by
SAR sagger or
SAR now it's not now it's not zero it's
still zero but uh but now it is not the
direct equation it's the lran for the
direct field all right what does it have
in it it has
terms so dagger derivatives of s those
are the kinds of things which
move a particle from one point to
another remember in the Klein Gordon
equation the kinetic term was associated
with the hopping of the particle from
one point to
another and that's what these terms are
it absorbs a particle and moves it to a
new point of SpaceTime that's what the
derivatives do they move it to a new
point of space time at the same time
they jiggle its spin in a certain way
that's uh that's what these kinetic
things are and the mass term is just a
term which takes a
particle absorbs it and emits it from a
point of space with no derivatives at
all it doesn't it just absorbs it and
emits it from the same spot that's the
lran for the dra
equation um and it's yeah
no no no okay I all right so you asked
me I hadn't used that language but I I
will now use that language
now
good just for those who are curious
about the more covariant language if you
take side dagger and you multiply it by
Beta that gives you something that it's
called
SAR if if you want to get back from SAR
to S you multiply by Beta why because
beta squ is equal to 1 all right so you
can write this you can rewrite this in
the following
way you write it as SAR beta that's just
side dagger d by
DT and then over here what we have then
we will have plus SAR beta Alpha sub I
derivative with respect to X by
S and then what about this one over here
sorry let's put a um yeah this one is
going to be S Daga beta M SI what will
that
be no no well it's just SAR m s msar m
m
plus M
SAR
s now if I change the name of these
symbols we can call beta gamma not why
not because it's connected with not
usually refers to time the uh four
coordinates of space time are the zero
component for time and 1 two 3 for space
so this one's usually called gamma not
beta is sometimes called in fact most
frequently in modern physics the alpha
beta notation is mostly abandoned and
you use gamma so this becomes SAR gamma
n
DT s and this one now we're going to
change the name beta time
Alpha just the product beta * Alpha I
we're going to call gamma
I SAR
gamma i d i
s plus M
sari that's the lran and now it has a
very very neat form you can think of
gamma n d by DT as being gamma n d by DX
n this is gamma i d by DX I it looks
like a nice covariant sort of four
Vector product of gamma matrices times
derivatives in other words you can write
the whole thing in the
form
SAR gamma mu d by DX mu let's just p d
by D mu now mu goes from 1 to 4 plus
m
s okay that's that's much uh more
elegant than the original form that D
act wrote
down these are also the alphas and betas
are called directa matrices the gamas
are also called D matri yeah you said
the S on the far left here was SAR and
you didn't
bar right side bar right all right but
all you have to remember though is that
side bar is not side
dagger it's side dagger with an extra
gamut right but this is the this is the
elegant form for the
equation in fact SAR s happens to be a
scalar and SAR gamma s is a four Vector
it has an index
mu so this is a this is a more elegant
way to present the direct equation the
dra L grangian the direct
equation is
just setting this equal to zero
okay the dular Gran looks like
this now from this point of
view let's just examine well let's
examine the various terms you know
there's a fifth direct Matrix anybody
know what it's
called gamma 5 what's
missing gamma four there's no gamma
four in fact it's just a a glitch
there's another there's one more gamma
Matrix which is called gamma 5 which
happens to be the product of gamma North
Gamma 1 gamma 2 gamma 3 it's called
gamma
5 uh it happens to be one
more
Matrix and in fact the igen vectors of
gamma 5 gamma 5^ squar is also equal to
one it has two igen values plus one and
minus
one and the two igen vectors or the two
igen values correspond to the left hand
nness on the right-handedness of uh of
the of the particles gamma 5 is called
helicity chirality excuse me
chirality
handedness chyro for hand you know like
uh K was the Greek word for
hand Chiron chyos KY something with a
chy c
cir chirality yeah gamma 5 is called
chirality and it can be plus or minus
one
and it corresponds to the handedness of
the two
particles
now if you work it out if you work out
the various things you'll find that this
term here does not couple the
left-handed and the right-handed
components of s the left-handed and
right-handed components of s mean the
things with Ian value + one and minus
one for gamma 5 but just think of them
as electrons or particles with a with a
right-handed uh helicity or a
left-handed
helicity these two
here sorry these four here do not
multiply left-handed times right-handed
just happens they don't you can work
that out from the by
yourselves this one does sar Time s
happens to
be it can happens to be it's right it
this
way happens to be side dagger left s
right plus side dagger
right s
left that's what it is so the mass term
here mixes up the left-handed and the
right-handed particles that's what a
mass is a direct mass is it's a termin
the lran seems Weir weird that it should
have anything to do with um uh with
um uh
inertia it's a term which causes a
left-handed firon to flip to a
right-handed firon to flip to a
left-handed firon and so forth and
that's what's over
here okay the other terms don't do that
so that means a massless feron has a
definite chirality the mass term flips
the chirality back and forth and back
and forth
um
yeah all right then we talked about a
class of interactions the weak
interactions let's in particular focus
on the Z the the emission and absorption
of ZB
Boons that is purely left-handed for
some odd reason for some odd
reason uh the
zebon only is emitted by left-handed
particles not by right-handed particles
this is not true of the photon this is
only true of the zon sorry the wban
zosan is a little more kinky it uh it
has asymmetric couplings to uh to
left-handed and
right-handed um but let's focus on the
W's they couple through only the
left-handed uh uh degrees of freedom so
that means that in effect with respect
to the charges with respect to the
transformation properties under the su2
the su2 that's connected with the w the
emission of w bosons the left-handed
firon is charged and the right-handed
Fon is
uncharged you're not allowed to put in a
lran something like this which would
take a Charged particle to an uncharged
particle it would mean a process in
which a Charged particle would come in
and get absorbed and uncharged partic go
out violates charge
conservation so this would not be a
legal uh term in a lran
that had a um a gauge symmetry which
only coupled to left-handed particles
all right then the question is how do
you get a Mass for fans we know that
electrons and quirks they all have
masses there something
wrong ah here's where the higs Bon comes
into play the Hig ban also plays the
role of a charged object with respect to
the su2 of uh of um weak
interactions in fact it's a doublet just
like the electron in nutrino are
doublets the higs boson is also a dublet
I didn't emphasize that and I'm not
going to emphasize it I've sort of
skirted around it uh the higs boson also
transforms under
su2 and roughly speaking in the way to
make this into a legitimate interaction
is to multiply by the appropriate higs
boson field here the higs boson if you
like carries
uh
carries a weak
charge which is either the same or
opposite depending on which component
we're talking about as the uh as the
weak charge of let's say the electron if
we're talking about electrons here the
right-handed particle has no charge with
respect to uh with respect to the weak
interactions so what we have to do is
put a higs boson here and a higs dagger
here this means the emission of a higs
boson and the emission of a anti-ig
boson if you like with the higs boson
carrying off the
charge of the left-handed uh particle
when it became the right-handed particle
so we introduce into the uh into the
lran something which takes a left-handed
firon emits a right-handed firon but
also allows a higs boson to be emitted
in such a way that the weak
charge of the electron or The Quirk or
whatever it is uh Escapes in the form of
the heg boson the higs
dublet and that would be the end of the
story except for the SP spontaneous
symmetry breaking which has to do with
the higs ffield getting an expectation
value the higs field well I think we
called it fi last time didn't
we I think we called it
fi let's just continue to call it fi and
we emit a fi particle
here that would be the end of the story
except that for whatever
reasons Nature has chosen the energetic
of the higs field this F here to have
one of these Mexican hat potential
energies why did it do that why did
nature do that we don't know okay but
we're very lucky that it did otherwise
um chemistry would go to
hell and uh things would be very very
unpleasant um but with one of these
upside down Mexican hat potentials that
means that fi
is equal to a number just the magnitude
of the higs field here which we called
f plus a fluctuation a fluctuation away
from that value and that fluctuation is
what we actually call the higs
field all right so let's go back now
what happens to this term what happens
to these terms in the lran they break up
into two
pieces not these two pieces but these
two pieces
one of
them is just oh I left out one thing
what did I leave out of this
expression a numerical number g g the
yukawa coupling let's call it g sub y
and there's a different G sub y for each
firon these two should be the
same all right G sub y is just a number
a pure number carries no dimensions
they called yukawa
couplings and
um where they came from I don't know
somebody wiser than me put them into the
Lan okay so here they
are all right now let's use the fact
that fi is equal to a nonfluctuating
part which we called f for the
non-fluctuating part we called it f
don't and for the fluctuating part we
called it h the higsbo sign that's not
my notation that's uh that's a standard
notation so this becomes
gy F times side dagger left s
right plus side dagger
right side
left plus
gy higs
field times the same
thing same thing
okay now we have a prediction for what
the number
F where did that came come from the
number F we obtained that same number F
went into the mass of the Z and W
bosons the shift of the higs field also
determined the mass of the Z and W
bosons once you've measured the mass of
the Z and W bosons and this was done a
long time ago they were measured masses
a measured about of order 100 gev 90 gev
something like that so that told us what
F
was that told us what what the number F
was F is a number of
about really 200 g for f okay so that's
a that's a it has units of mass
incidentally F has units of mass 200
gev ah once we know that from Z and W
physics then from the masses of the Fons
we can read off what these yukawa
couplings
are once we know for example the
electron yukawa coupling is some very
very small number why because the
electron is much lighter than the z& W
the um yukawa coupling for the top Quark
that's large why because the top Quark
is so heavy so the masses of the quarks
wind up being these yukara couplings
times F and so far we've really gotten
out no more than we put in we've gotten
out no more than we put in we got F from
the masses of well a little bit more but
basically Mass the the masses of ZW
system we got
F and then from the masses of the firion
we got the ukawa
couplings all right so if that's all
there was we would have put in as much
as we got out but now we also have
something else we have gy higs times
things like let's just call them s
dagai these are terms in lran which take
a firon this in this could be an
electron it could be a whatever it
happens to be which take a fon absorb it
and Reit it plus a higs boson so these
are then processes where let's say
electron or it could be muon or it could
be TOA or it could be some
quk
um emits a higs
boson or it could be a HX boson coming
along and decaying into an electron and
a positron same
diagram Okay so once the higs boson
materializes as a particle in the
laboratory we should know what the
various Decay Decay rates are for it to
Decay to the different kinds of electron
positron electron muon anti muon or
whatever we'll know all of the
interactions between the higs boson and
the Fons and be able to predict all the
Decay rates all the higb on Decay
rates uh obviously it'll prefer to Decay
to heavier parts particles as long as
there's enough energy because these
yukawa couplings are larger ukawa
couplings are the coupling constant for
the higs to break up into uh its
constituents into its Decay
products so at the moment I mean
hexology is a um is a pure
theory in in the sense that uh it's uh
predicted by the theory there seems to
be no other way to make it
mathematically
consistent but but neither the higs nor
the direct couplings to these particles
and so forth have been detected that
will happen well I hope it will
happen
um and so there's a lot of predictive
power the theory also already has an
enormous amount of predictive power
predictive power in the interactions of
the Z's and the W's which are
experimentally detected the interaction
of Z's and the W's not only with respect
to the firion but with respect to each
other
Z's yeah how would you actually predict
the Decay time I don't mean going
through all the nitty-gritty details but
I mean sort of how I mean how would you
set it up to to actually make that
prediction well you calculate a findan
diagram you calculate a findan
diagram
uh you can just think of it as
Elementary quantum mechanics this gives
you a term in the hamiltonian which
takes the higs boson to a pair of
particles and it just gives you the
transition amplitude which you
square and once you've squared it you
integrate it or sum it over all the
final states there an integral to do and
uh that gives you the Decay
rate um it's a uh it's a standard
calculation that uh is basically a
finement diagram if you like this gives
you the amplitud
ude you square the amplitude to get the
Decay rate squaring the amplitude you
can just do by putting this right on top
of itself like that here the amplitude
is
squared and that becomes a Fineman
diagram you calculate the finan diagram
by Fan's rules and one of the things
that comes out of it is the Decay rate
so uh uh but uh this is uh more than
we're going to do here that's we have to
do uh
so it's it's a very very definite uh
calculation within standard Quantum
field
Theory and uh it's the kind of
calculation we've been doing since the
1930s
so so it's it's quite well
known the only things that you have to
put in which are new are the values of
these coupling constants masses of
particles and so
forth okay so that was
the masses of ferons the masses of the
uh Z and W bosons all of them being
proportional to this constant F why
don't we talk about the uh the higs uh
itself let's talk about the Dynamics of
the higs
bosone the dynamic is really all
contained in this Mexican hat
potential the minimum of the Mexican hat
potential tells you how much the field
is shifted and it tells you what f is
all right you can make up different
potentials to that have this shape
there's a favorite one which actually
has some uh some important theoretical
significance uh
and it goes as
follows let's go to the origin over here
at the origin the higs potential is a
sort of upside down
Parabola let's forget what it does far
from the origin let's just concentrate
on near the origin an upside down
Parabola means something like minus
let's call it mu^
2 5^
2 and uh it's traditional to put a two
in here
it's just traditional minus because it's
an upside down Parabola remember if it
was plus mu^ 2 f s i^ squ what would you
call this
term you would call this term the mass
of the higs BOS on you would call MU the
mass of the higs
boson or you would really call mu^ squ
the square of the mass of the higs boson
making it negative is a little bit weird
it's as if there was an imaginary mass
for the higs BOS on but don't worry
there's nothing wrong with this it's
perfectly okay to have a potential which
is upside down the only thing which is
unusual about it is putting the field at
the origin is not a stable position it
tends to roll off and roll down the
hill whereas if the mass term was
positive it would oscillate about the
top about the central position here so
the field does not oscillate about the
top because of this minus 5^ s now if
all you had was minus 5^ s it would just
go down and down and down and the field
would just run away to Infinity there
would be no ground state to the system
there would be no vacuum there vacuum is
the state of lowest energy there would
be no state of lowest energy so we've
got to put in something to keep it from
running away to Infinity we better put
in something to turn it up simplest
thing to turn it up is Plus
Lambda where Lambda is just a number
pure
number Time 5 to
4 why do I want to put in five why not
the five cubed the five to the five to
the 5ifth why not odd Powers because we
want to keep it symmetric on both sides
this was an important uh aspect of this
potential was to keep it nice and
symmetric right so 5 to the 4th is
symmetric five
Cub is not this is the next thing you
can put in you can put in all sorts of
things to higher Powers here they're not
so important they're not so important
the most important one is fight to the
fourth and expanding the potential in a
power series you can put in more but
this is the most important thing and in
fact it's also traditional to put a four
over here you'll see why in a moment a
two over here and a four over here all
what is this number this number is
called a CTIC coupling constant quartic
because it has five to the 4th it has it
is dimensionless it's a pure
number right we think we know something
about that pure
number not from direct experimental
evidence but from a lot of indirect
evidence and what we know about that
number from somewhat indirect uh
properties of weak interactions is that
it's small but not absurdly small
probably about uh 1% probably about um
uh
uh one 01 or something like that uh
compared to the numbers we're going to
be thinking about later this is a number
which is of order of magnitude one it's
not 10 the minus 20 it's not 10 Theus 15
or anything like that so just think of
it as a number for the moment of order
one it's also dimensionless
mu is not dimensional dimensional as it
has units of a
mass okay now let's try to find out what
f is f is the position at the minimum
here all we have to do is minimize this
with respect to
fi we cooked it up so that it would have
a minimum a rapidly falling quadratic
term and then taken over by incidentally
near the origin this is smaller than
this right 5 to the 4th is smaller than
5^ squ near the origin so this has not
got much effect near the origin it picks
up steam and eventually becomes much
bigger than 5^ S when you go to large fi
so that turns it back up that's the
logic okay let's just find the minimum
of f sorry the minimum of
V with respect to fi and that will tell
us how much the field gets
shifted all right that's easy we just
differentiate with respect to fi
the derivative of 5^ 2 is 2 that eats up
this two down here that's why I put the
two down there minus mu ^ 2 F this is
the derivative of V with respect to fi
plus Lambda which is a number of order
of magnitude one 5
cubed I also put the four down here so
it would kill the four when I
differentiated with respect to 5 to the
4th and we set that equal to zero
all right now we can divide by
fi we divide by
five make this 5^
squared and what do we get we get 5^
2 is equal to mu^ 2 over
Lambda again Lambda is an ordinary
number don't think of it as very big or
very small
small this is the value of F at the
minimum it's also called
f that's also the shift of the field F
and so f
s becomes mu^ 2 over
Lambda again I emphasize Lambda is not
the interesting number here it's a
common Garden variety number like uh
like one or tenth or 100 or something
like that it's not very big that's for
sure okay
um f is controlled by
mu f is also approximately the mass of
the Z and the B the Z and the W boson
it's also the thing which comes into the
mass of the Fons where are they all of
the particles have masses proportional
to
F let's take the square root of this
so it's mu or F or mu which is the
controlling factor which controls all of
these
masses all of them all the masses of
water all the particles that we know
about okay that raises an interesting
question why are all of the particles
that we know
about controlled by the same
phenomenon namely f why aren't there
particles which have masses without
spontaneous symmetry breaking we can
certainly make up a theory of such
particles for example just make up a
particle whose left-handed and
right-handed components both have weak
charge then we have no reason to put
this fi in there we wouldn't put the FI
in there and you could put any mass that
you like in front of it and it's
perfectly symmetric so if there was a
particle
uh which
was whose left and right-handed uh
components both interacted with the weak
interactions the same
way they could have a mass which was not
proportional to
F all kinds of other particles could all
particles that don't have any weak
interactions at all if there was such
particles could have uh could have
masses which are not controlled by F the
general thinking which will come to
which will come to I'll explain why this
is the general thinking is that the
natural Mass scale for particle physics
is
enormous much much higher than the
masses of any of the Ordinary Elementary
particles it's thought that only this
one number f is the unusual number in
physics the very very small Mass
scale whose Origins are at present
unknown but what is thought and I'll
explain as we well this this quarter
next quarter
various
points the idea that really the only
Mass the only Mass parameter the only
small Mass parameter in
nature is this F
here and those
particles which by necessity have to
have masses proportional to
F why because it's in the nature of
their
mathematics that they would have to be
massless if there was no shift of f only
those particles are light enough to have
been detected at present that's the
belief that's a very widespread belief
that that there's a good reason why all
the particles have masses proportional
to F because any that don't probably
have masses which are much much larger
but still we have to explain the
smallness of F small compared to what
well that's an interesting question
small compared with what what is the
natural Mass scale uh for elementary
particle
physics so that's where I think uh we
want to go
next h mass that's one possible Mass yes
yes all right uh let's see I think it uh
we'll take a break in two minutes but um
yes one possible Mass which we'll talk
about in a few minutes after the break
is the plunk Mass another is a so-called
unification Mass which I'll I'll show
you what it is um these masses are
typically 16 or 17 orders of magnitude
well let me see
um 15 orders of
magnitude heavier than the mess than the
than F 15 orders of magnitude heavier
than the Z boson for
example so what we're left with then is
a puzzle why is this F quantity so small
once we can understand why the F
quantity is so small it drags down the
masses of all the other particles it
drags them down simply because they
cannot have
mass other than proportional to F they
would naturally be massless in a world
without spontaneous symmetry breaking so
yeah would you say that again about the
15 orders of
yeah the natural all right f is a number
of about 100
gev all right that's sounds like a lot
of it sounds like a big Mass all right
the other Mass scales which come into
particle physics which we know about the
other possibly much more fundamental
Mass scales are much much heavier than
that 15 orders of magnitude heavier than
that and what particles correspond to
that none that we've ever discovered
obviously you're right any we predicted
y yeah well well yes of course particles
we predicted but why did we predict them
15 orders of magnitude
higher in other words when uh when I say
that there are other Mass scales that we
know about we know about them from
something so the question is where do we
know about them if we've never seen if
we've never seen them if we've never
seen particles of those masses we'll
talk about that uh after the
break I GA that in U in uh these very
very low temperature uh matter o kinds
of things there all sorts of analogs to
part physics and but aside from that is
there any common inate physics or any
common example that PS light yes yes all
right so you you asked about bza
condensates so AB boa condensation or
more precisely super
fluidity which is similar to AB boa
condensation it's a
condensation of um helium atoms okay
okay helium atoms helium atoms are of
course not Elementary particles okay but
on some scale they are Elementary
particles uh if you're if you're
interested in um in Scales of water
molecular size a helium nucleus is an
elementary particle and it can be
described by a
field okay that field naturally an
ordinary vacuum has a value zero just
corresponding to no helium atoms present
okay spontaneous symmetry com breaking
can happen which can shift the value of
the uh of the helium field when that
happens in the same way that uh that f
is a shift of the um of the higs field
when that happens it's roughly speaking
uh called a bza condensation when the
boa condensation happens it
spontaneously breaks a certain
Symmetry and that's called and it it
creates super
fluidity but
if the helium atom were
charged if the helium not the helium
nucleus the helium atom if the helium
atom were
charged it would behave like the higs
boson and make a Mass for the
photon now does that ever happen
anything like it ever happened yes it
does in a
superconductor electrons can pair up and
bind together in the superconductor very
weakly bound Pairs and those pairs of
electrons have charge
to right they're not helium atoms
they're not neutral here in the atoms
they're called Cooper Pairs and they're
bound configurations of electron not
electron and positron but electron and
electron separated H the Cooper pairs
aren't they separated they're
separated they're not very far separated
in space they're separated the opposite
ends of the firmy
surface um right uh no they're think of
them as particles uh in first
approximation think of them as particles
they're charged
particles and then they condense they
condense which means the field for this
pair of particles gets shifted you can
think of that PE field is really just
being the product of the electron field
with itself describing two electrons or
you can think of it as a new object
which carries charge
two when that field gets shifted it
creates a condensate of of Cooper pairs
it creates a kind of super fluidity for
the Cooper pairs but it's now a super
fluid of charged particles it becomes
the higs phenomena it's of course a
superconductor and the superconductor
in essentially every possible way
behaves like the higs phenomenon Photon
gets mass now it's a tiny tiny Mass
because the scales are so terribly
different but uh the um the Compton
wavelength of the uh
of the photon becomes
finite and it behaves very very much
like this uh like this spontaneously
shifted higs field in fact the phenomena
was first discovered in the context of
uh
superconductors and uh was rediscovered
entirely independently by uh by higs and
other
people okay let's take a little break uh
when
um you begin at the primordial
description of Elementary particles you
begin with lran and in the L grangian
there are a collection of
parameters such as masses of particles
charges of
particles and uh there're sort of the
input on the other hand they're very
rarely if ever the actual measured
quantities the measured quantities that
you actually measure are usually the
product of all kinds of interactions and
things that take
place uh between the high frequency
modes of a system and low frequency
modes of the system which renormalize or
change the values of the parameters that
you associate with experimental
observations an example is electric
charge so let's talk about that a little
bit and how charge gets
renormalized not going to do any
calculations calculations you'll have to
go and get a book and uh and try to
follow it but the phenomena the
phenomena is uh is a fairly simple one
that's well
known it occurs in condensed metaphysics
in fact it just occurs in classical uh
um electricity and magnetism associated
with um uh Electric what's it called
dialectric dialectric thank you with the
dialectric
materials and
conductors
the actual observable charge normally
observed charge of an object is defined
by the kulum
law but the kulum law at large
separation the asmic force between two
charges when they're far apart
and that Force as you well
know is the product of the charges let's
call it E1 E2 let let's take them to be
equal charges and in particular let's
suppose they have a charge of the
electron just to be simple then it's
just
e^2 uh divided R 2 or in the potential
energy just e^2 /
R all right so you take two charges far
apart and you measure the charge you
measure the force between them
uh at any given distance it will not be
precisely given by this formula but if
you ASM totically separate them then
you'll find ASM totically with respect
to R the force between them or the
potential energy between them uh goes
like e^2 over
R um attractive for opposite charges
repulsive for like
charges and that defines if you like the
charge of a particle kulum law at
spatially very large
separations now if in a
material you do this you take charges in
a material or even just the air and you
separate them and uh see what the force
LW is you'll find that it's not exactly
given by the
formula uh in which you go to the
particle physics table the particle
physics table of particle properties
read off the electric charge
of the system typically you won't read
off the electric charge of a uh of an
ordinary chunk of material but you might
happen to know how many electrons or how
many uh how many excess uh protons or
electrons are in it so you might know
it's charge in units of the charge of
the electron you take them apart and you
discover no the force is always a little
bit less than that always a little bit
less than that unless you're an absolute
vacuum an absolute vacuum completely
empty space by
definition the electric charge is uh
what you
measure by measuring the force at a
large distance now what is it that
happens in a
material uh let's begin with a
conductor with an electric
conductor what happens to a charge
that's put into the
conductor well the charge creates some
electric field for example suppose it's
a plus charge it it creates an outward
electric electric field the electric
field creates a current the current uh
the current starts charg is moving and
until the charge is completely
discharged until it's completely
discharged in other words until the
current until the charge has gone out to
the boundary of the
conductor that that the flow of charge
doesn't stop okay so the flow the charge
flows until the charged object let's
draw the charged object over over here
there it
is charge FL flows away from
it collects on the boundary but let's
put the boundary off an alpha centuri
someplace and of course an opposite
charge so if this is plus an opposite
charge cloud is found around it that
completely discharges it so that outside
there's
no electric field at all and no more
reason for the charges to flow
now these charges are of course bound to
the uh to the charge to the positive
charge they're bound to it and the whole
thing forms a neutral structure if you
take another negative charge over here
exactly the opposite thing will happen
to it it will create some plus charge
around
it same deal the charges will flow until
it's completely neutralized and now you
take these two charges you thought you
had two charges to begin with you
evaluate or measure the force between
them at large distances and you find out
that there is
none okay
so the charge that you put in to begin
with is not the experimental charge at
the end of the day the experimental
charge at the end of the day in this
case is just plain
zero okay now what happens as you start
moving the two charges let's suppose
they're really small and you start
moving them closer and closer
together and is this is this screening
screening this is
screen okay supposing these charges are
really small in particular they're
smaller than the clouds around them that
form the clouds around them are
controlled by various properties of the
metal and so forth and the electrons
moving in the metal and we imagine
making these charges even smaller we
bring them really close together we
bring them so close together that the
screening cloud that can't get between
them typically there's a scale for the
screening
Cloud it's
controlled uh by the Dynamics of the
electrons in the in the in the in the
system and the screening Cloud the
particles making up the screening Cloud
typically have a certain distance
between them and that distance controls
the size of the screening
Cloud when you bring these two particles
closer than the screening Cloud they're
no longer screened they actually feel
each other's raw basic uh charge and you
see that there's a Kum force between
them which is the usual e^2 over
R okay so you could say then that the
charge of the electron or the charge of
the particle in this case is really a
function of
distance in the case of the conductor e
of R is zero at very large
R it's what ever the ordinary charge of
the particle is a very small R and the
force law instead of being just plain
e^2 over R has e^2 of R / R this is just
a definition of E2 of R if you like I
don't put anything new into it by
calling it e^ s of R but it does uh it
does uh have a nice sound to it it's
called The Running charge running as a
function of distance between
them okay now what happen if you have
something less
extreme uh than a uh than a conductor
for example a dialectric a dialectric if
you like has electrons which are bound
to the atoms electrons are bound to the
atoms but they're free to shift a little
bit if you like you can almost think of
the electrons as being on
Springs where the one end of the spring
the electron is attached to the other
end of the
spring uh the uh the ion the positively
charged ion is attached and ordinarily
the electron moves symmetrically
vibrates symmetrically of course this is
not really a good uh picture of of an
atom but it's good enough for our
purposes the electron oscillates and
vibrates back and forth symmetrically
about the uh the atom so on the average
the dipole moment of the atom is zero
but now you put the atom into an
electric field and what happens is the
electron CL shifts a little
bit it shifts a little bit leaving a
dipole left
over
Uh current doesn't flow charge just
shifts a little bit because they're
bound to the uh to the um
atoms okay so now what happens if you
put a charge into
a dialectric well a very similar
phenomenon happens let's suppose we put
a minus charge in over
here all the ions
are they're heavy they don't move very
much but the electrons which are bound
to them by the Springs move out away
from the uh from the central atom what
does that leave that leaves a little bit
of plus charge here but it doesn't
completely screen the
charge uh it screens some fraction of
the charge charge so that if you look
very very far away from the charged
particle you'll find that the field the
electric field is diminished by a
certain fraction but it doesn't go to
zero very far away okay the fraction is
controlled by the dialectric constant
dialectric constant will tell you uh how
what the uh what the screening is so
again you'll find that a large
separation this plus charge and this
minus charge don't satisfy the expected
Kum law that you might have expected
from the actual let's call it the bare
charge of these particles but it's
diminished by this um by this effect
it's diminished the kulum law is correct
but with a diminished value of the
charge so in this case you would also
have an e^2 of r or an e of R again if
you bring the charges very close
together so that they're within the
screening Cloud then you feel the full
strength of the be charge so again uh
e^2 is a function of r in this case it
wouldn't go to zero and infinity it
would just go to some constant uh
fraction of the original charge again
the concept of a running
charge all right now exactly this
phenomenon is really is exactly this
phenomenon happens in Quantum field
Theory and the origin of it is the pairs
let's take Quantum electrod Dynamics in
Quantum
electrodynamics uh the vacuum is full of
electron positron
pairs okay there are finding
diagrams where electrons positrons are
created by photons even just even just
electron positron loops with no uh with
no photons and they inhabit the vacuum
if you
like the other way you can think about
it is you can think about it in terms of
Drax negative energy C the vacuum is
filled with this negative energy C or
you can imagine that there are electron
positron pairs in the vacuum what
happens when an electric field comes
along the electric field will shift the
positrons one way and shift the
electrons the other way so that every
little virtual pair electron positron
pair will become polarized polarized in
exactly the same way that atoms become
polarized by an electric field the plus
charge is Shifting one way the minus
charge is Shifting the other way that's
what happens in the vacuum when you put
an electric field on
uh okay that's uh that's step number one
step number two of course you put in
what you thought was an original bare
charge of magnitude e the charges in the
vacuum rearrange a little bit the vacuum
is basically a dialectric it's basically
a dialectric the charges shift a little
bit and in such a way that negative
charges are screened by a little bit of
positive charge from these virtual Pairs
and positive charge charges are screened
by a little bit of negative
charge the upshot is the charge that's
felt at a large distance is not the same
as the numerical value of the charge
that you put into the lran which is
usually called the bare electric
charge but again you start moving the
electrons closer and closer to each
other and at some point they get closer
than the size of the screening Cloud but
there's one difference in this case in
this case there's the there is no set
distance that the electron positrons
tend to be
from be separated by the right statement
is that the separation between the
electron positron pairs depends on their
energy uh the higher the energy of the
virtual pair the closer they will
be so there will be electron positron
pairs which form relatively big let's
call them atoms they're not atoms but
let's call them um Atomic uh neutral
systems there will be ones of higher
virtual energy which are smaller ones of
yet higher virtual energy which are even
smaller ones which are higher energy
which are even smaller okay so what
happens when you put the charge in um
and and bring another charge closer and
closer and closer at first you will
bring them close enough that they'll be
within the
distance of the low energy virtual
pairs the low energy virtual pairs will
no longer be able to screen the
charge and so the charge will look a
little bit smaller sorry a little bit
bigger than it would when they were far
apart why when they were far apart they
were completely screen not completely
screen but they were screened by all
possible virtual pairs you bring them a
little bit closer the low energy virtual
pairs which had a large separation
between
them you bring the charges closer than
that and the low energy virtual pairs
are no longer important than screening
but the higher energy virtual pairs are
still doing some screening you bring
them a little
closer
the higher energy pair
fall out of the equation because they're
too far apart and yet higher energy ones
are still there the effect is that that
e^2 of R is a function which keeps
changing and changing and changing with
r uh it doesn't stop changing at some
small at some particular small distance
the closer and closer you bring the
electron together the larger the charge
will appear to be so if you were to plot
by virtue of the fact that there are
pairs of every every possible energy in
the vacuum so if you want the plot the
electric
charge as a function
of radial
separation let's plot it as a function
of inverse radial
separation inverse radial separation is
like energy the closer things are
together the higher their energy so
let's plot it as a function of uh
inverse separation 1 / R which is also
related to energy or momentum or
whatever then the electric charge that
you'll see will
increase it'll increase very slowly in
fact it's a very slow logarithmic
increase it doesn't increase
rapidly that's why it's very hard to see
in an experiment it's a logarithmic
gradual increase of the size of the size
of an electric charge as you study
smaller and smaller distance
phenomenon it's also true for example
electric charge comes into calculations
of
scattering of electrons if you scatter
electrons at a low energy they only get
within a certain distance of each other
the higher the energy you scatter them
the closer those electrons can get to
each other by virtue of the uncertainty
principle
and when you do the calculation you have
to put in the running charge if you Cal
if you scatter electrons at enormously
high energy they behave as if they had a
larger charge than at uh at smaller
distances so that brings us to the idea
of running charge right what is the
fundamental charge what is the most
fundamental value of the charge is it
the one at long distances no that's the
one that's controlled by all of this
complicated screening taking place as
you get as you get to smaller and
smaller distances you sort of Peel away
the screening
Cloud as you get the smaller and smaller
distances you peel away more and more of
the screening Cloud so it's really at
the smallest distances where the basic
parameter that you put into the lran and
the bare charge manifest itself okay
yeah how small small start see a
significant
effect
uh well you start seeing a measurable
effect at but a high Precision
measurable effect at a few times uh at a
at about the Compton wavelength of the
electron so what's that 10 Theus 11 C uh
Compton wavelength of the electron um uh
the electron is half an
me so that's about 10 Theus 11 cm
about 10 Theus 11 cenm you start to see
uh you start to see the running of the
charge but this thing
continu well it would keep going on if
the physics didn't change somehow at
very small distances we don't know what
the physics is a very very small you
just said something about sort of
implying that the small one was there
there we don't know what happens
actually at very small
right that's that's right that's right
we don't know what happens at very small
so we can only extrapolate a certain
yeah so for blue arms it's kind of the
opposite thing there's some anti screen
it does it
does well that's a more complicated
phenomenon more complicated phenomena
that's closely connected with the fact
that gluons interact with
gluons and because gluons interact with
gluons in a very nonlinear kind of way
the effect is actually the
opposite right this
is you go to infinitely small distances
and you measure at infinitely small
distances the interaction and that's the
bare electric charge but you'll never
get to infinitely small distances
because approaches something no it
doesn't ASM totically it just keeps
growing and growing and growing yeah
logarithmic function is unbounded right
right right so it keeps growing until
something happens that was not taken
into account by these
calculations what could it be a smallest
distance in the world the plun distance
something else happens
and from experimental physics we don't
know what terminates
this we certainly believe it's
terminated at the plunk length this
physics certainly doesn't make sense
uh but there has to be a particular LM
you say that's bare electric
charge uh
so let's call
it but you see you can compensate you
can change that length and if you also
at the same time change what you called
the bare charge it would
compensate right so at any given level
you could terminate it call that charge
the bear charge at that
length or change the length scale if you
appropriately and judiciously change the
value of the bare charge where it comes
out at the low energy end won't uh won't
know about
it right so that's the phenomena of
renormalization changing things in such
a way as to keep the physics the
experimentally known physics
T is that what you're zooming in and
attenuating is that you're zooming in
and looking at closer and closer
distances now of course we don't do that
experimentally so we do that in our mind
and we ask how do we have to change the
physics at smaller and smaller distances
to keep it fixed at experimentally
accessible distances how do we have to
change the electric charge as we go to
smaller and smaller distances in order
to keep the physics fixed at any given
wavelength so what this is telling us is
that as we go to smaller and smaller
more and more refined
description more and more fine grain
description the value of the electric
charge that we have to put into the into
the bare description has to grow now as
I said that will change at some point
where the physics uh that Quantum
electrodynamics gives way to something
else okay so that's the electric
charge yeah yeah does does the same
phenomena happen with gravity the
equations are somewhat similar we'll
talk about uh it's quite a different
phenomenon but uh we'll we'll we'll come
to it uh perhaps today I don't know if
we'll come to it today maybe okay now
let's talk about the strong
interactions the strong interactions
things are more complicated let me
remind you of what we learned about the
force law between
quirks the force law between
quirks does not behave like e^2 / R what
happens is some new phenomen PHA where
the flux lines that come out of quirks
these are not the electromagnetic flux
lines these are the flux lines of qcd
they're called chromoelectric flux lines
attract each other they attract each
other in a way that does not happen in
electrodynamics it's the self
interaction between
gluons all right and that has the effect
of turning the kulum field into long
long tubl likee
structures which are sort of squeezed by
the vacuum into these long tub likee
structures the effect of this is as you
separate
quirks the energy
grows linearly with the separation
between between them you create this
Turkish taffy gooey stuff in between
them and the energy of it grows simply
as the length of the gooey thing between
them that means that the force
law the energy grows linearly what does
the force all right so let's write that
down instead of going instead of the
energy growing like
e^2 over
R it's just a it just grows linearly
with r so this is the wrong formula we
should have put here perhaps e squared
or something like e^ stimes
R let's not call it uh something times
R well we can either say we had
completely the wrong Theory or we can
say that e s is growing like R squar we
can say the picture from electrodynamics
that charges are
screened simply the opposite happens
that e s grows with separation something
happens in this nonlinear effect here
which is quite the opposite and so e s
grows with separation incidentally at
very small distances again distances
which are so small smaller than the size
of these flux tubes it reverts back to
e^2 over
R okay so it reverts back to the good
old kulum law but another way of saying
it is that instead of e^2 as a function
of distance getting larger with distance
it actually gets smaller with distance
e squ is getting smaller no sorry with
inverse
distance it's getting smaller with
inverse distance larger with distance
smaller with inverse distance so
therefore if I
plot the quantum
chromodynamics uh coupling constant it
will fall as a function of inverse
R like
that what about the one for the weaken
interactions well the weak interactions
are sort of in
between they sort of in between uh they
have similarities with both they're in
between they go like that well maybe not
as
fast it's an interesting and quite
remarkable
fact that if you actually take the
standard
model and you work out how the charges
first of all you need to know what the
various coupling constants are in the
laboratory those are the ones that
control physics at whatever scales
you've done your
experiment 100 G or whatever and you put
in their
values and then you run them using just
the standard model the the polarization
of the vacuum and all the properties
from the standard model these three
numbers
more or less come together at a common
point they more or less come together at
a common point now in a more refi well
in a uh in the super symmetric version
of the theory which we will talk about
next time a little bit next quarter they
come together with rather High Precision
about 1% about 1% okay they come
together about 1% that looks like
there's something happening at some
energy which is unifying these forces
their coupling constants seem to be the
same at some high energy here if you
just extrapolate these curves the curves
are calculable of course you have to
assume that no new physics comes
in that no new physics comes in or if
new physics comes in you have to take it
into
account new physics might shift these
curves a little bit in the super
symmetric version of the the
the these three numbers come together
very nicely to about 1% at an energy of
about 10 to the 16th
gev why is that energy so high it's
because these curves vary
logarithmically they vary
slowly okay when things vary slowly they
vary slowly and so it takes a
long range of scales before they come
together and they come together at about
10 to the 16th gev 10 to 14th times
larger than the mass of the
W all right so it's some huge energy it
looks from these curves that some kind
of unification is taking place there now
is this good enough to uh is this uh
it's um a relatively High Precision
agreement in the super symmetric theory
in the non-supersymmetric theory it's
not such High Precision agreement but
it's tantalizing and it's
interesting
uh that uh that this is the the tendency
for things all right if this is correct
you might guess that the
fundamental length scale of particle
physics of the standard model is up at
this 10 to the 15 G it's where the input
seems to be simplest simplest and that
the three coupling constants seem to be
the same
[Music]
uh we'll talk about what that means
mathematically it has a very deep ma
could have a very deep mathematical
meaning but for the moment it's just an
observation about numbers that they come
together uh at a particular energy now
that energy also happens to be the place
if you were to plot the strength of
gravitational
forces gravitational forces are very
weak at large distances but I'm going to
show you why in a moment they get
stronger and stronger and stronger at
small distances not only because of the
usual 1 / r s in the force but above and
beyond that the forces of gravitation
become stronger and stronger and if you
will to lay on top of that uh let's see
the forces of gravitation would become
strong at small distances so that would
mean gravitational forces which are
incredibly weak at long dist
distances would do something like that
and they don't quite all cross at the
same place but they cross within a
factor you remember these are
logarithmic curves they cross within a
couple of orders of magnitude of each
other the gravitational the weak the
electromagnetic and the strong
interaction cross all within a couple of
Decades of energy of each other or a
couple of Decades of length scale
at about somewhere between 10 to the
16th 17th 18th uh
gev so what all this means especially
the gravitational side of it we don't
know but if there is a unification scale
and if this really does correspond to
some Unity between the three forces it
looks like it happens at a scale which
is not too different than the plunk
scale the plunk scale is the scale where
gravity would be comparable to the other
forces so let's talk a little bit
about gravitational forces and why I say
that gravity gets stronger at small
distances
uh ordinarily now we're going to talk
about what happens to gravitational
forces as you vary the uh distance
scale and the only Point here is that
when you understand how gravity depends
on length scale you'll find out that
gravity sort of falls on the same
uh uh ball park with the other forces at
Scales which are very small that gravity
is really no weaker than uh than these
other forces okay so to understand this
we first have to erase the Blackboard a
little bit
we're used to thinking that um that the
force La of gravity is um 1 r squ or
Kum be surprised if I told you it's
really 1 / R cubed at very small
distances you wouldn't be surprised
but you
wouldn't okay so let's go through why
it's 1 R Cub at very small distances the
reason is we write down what do we write
down we write Force let's work let's
work with Force this time we worked with
energy before it doesn't matter which we
work with force is equal to m
m uh two particles masses um R 2 and
Newton's constant right that's the force
between two particles all right now this
is a nonrelativistic formula this is the
formula for particles at
rest when particles have a high energy
or when objects have a high energy it's
energy that gravitates and not uh and
not mass not rest Mass um a moving
object will gravitate more than an
object at rest if you take a box full of
high energy particles the high energy
particles will gravitate more than they
would if they were brought to rest
within the box so the right formula or a
a more correct formula a more correct
formula is to put
here use E =
mc² or m m not m squ e = mc^2 or better
yet m = e over c^2 and put in here
energy of particles e
e over C over C4 I believe right over C4
all right so this is a Formula which is
more accurate when the particles are
relativistic okay now let's go to
quantum mechanics and imagine bringing
two particles very close together much
closer together than their compon
wavelengths because of the uncertainty
principle if we've brought them close
together and we know that they're close
together that means that their momentum
is extremely uncertain to say that the
momentum is extremely uncertain you can
say that the momentum is very large
roughly speaking if you brought them to
within a distance r of each
other the momentum of
them must be at least of order what is
it
um H bar over R
right okay
now what about the energy of these
particles the energy of these particles
you might think well energy of a
particle at rest is MC
s if it has a little bit of velocity you
add plus 12 mv^
2 sorry 1 m v ^ 2 over
2 but what happens when the momentum
gets really large when R gets very small
when R gets very small these particles
become highly
relativistic why their momentum gets
much larger than any pre-assigned number
when they get very very close together
what's the energy of a particle a
relativistic particle with momentum p
relativistic means it's moving with
almost the speed of light anybody
remember what is
it no that's non no that's non
relativistic completely no no no the
energy is p * the speed of
light right P times the speed of light
okay so we can now say p is H over
R and now we can plug this into the
force between
particles okay so what is it f
is equal to HR squ let's just uh the the
particles come close together let's
assume they both have about the same
energy which is a good assumption so
that's HR
squar c
s over R 2 that's just e^2 here E1 *
E2 uh that's this Factor here then
there's a c to the 4th in the
denominator from here there's a
g and another R 2 so R to the
4th did I get it
right
right the C squ is cancel yeah well they
don't cancel c
squared all right when I said the force
LW was one over R Cub I meant the energy
not the uh not the uh not the force the
force is one over R to the
4th so when you bring particles really
close
together squeeze them by whatever means
either an accelerator accelerates them
to very high energy so they can get very
very close together or you put them in a
box and squeeze well no box is going to
hold particles uh that are that
relativistic
but somehow or another when the
particles get that close together the um
the force law is quite different than
kulum it's 1 / R to
4th okay now let's ask the following
question yeah we're talking
gravitational force here so it's an
attractive Force it's an attractive
Force
right and it is much more potent at
small distances than it is large
distances 1/ R to the 4th is much much
bigger than 1 / R than 1/ R this is one
R square this is because the
relativistic speed up causes the mass to
increase but not the charge to increase
right so right right exactly exactly so
exactly so okay now let's ask at what
length scale
R is the gravitational force
approximately the same order of
magnitude as the electromagnetic force
let's do a little let's um there's the
electric charge the electron's electric
charge is a pure number it happens to be
fairly small let's forget it but not not
ridiculously small it's a fairly small
number of something like a 10th or
something like that um in natural
natural
units
um so for first round we could just set
the electric charge of an electron equal
to one for Simplicity and then we could
ask at what length scale is the force
the gravitational force between a pair
of particles the same as the
electromagnetic force let's say a pair
of
electrons does that ever happen at
ordinary scales electric forces are
vastly larger than Electro than gravit
gravitational forces electric forces as
you bring them closer together because
the gravitational forces increase like
one R to 4th eventually the
gravitational force will cross the uh uh
the electrostatic force and smaller
distances will become even more
important even larger so let's see where
that happens to find out where that
happens we should set this
equal to
e^2 over R
2 for Simplicity for the moment let's
just set the electric charge equal to to
one it's not equal to one it's about a
tenth or something about uh that's
smaller than one e h g or E it uh G or E
you just erased G oh sorry I didn't mean
to erase G how do I do
that e
e Let's uh let's uh simplify and put a
one here which is not too wrong e squ is
really something like about a tenth okay
but it's not too bad it's approximately
right now we can read off from this at
what scale
these two kinds of forces become equal
to each other just multiply by R to
4th this becomes R 2ar
here now take the square root of it
right did I
uh something
wrong you had R4 be r s
now it's R squ yeah
okay I think I made a mistake I still
think I made a
mistake
h no but it's not right wait
um yeah know the
answer uh H Bar C over c^2 R 4 is 1/ R 2
right so I have H bar G over C
HR G over
C is equal to
R it's r s not
R it was an
R there was an R to 4th here
right and then there was a 1 over R 2
here so I got an R 2 here right
R right on both sides what you read out
sounded like you just taking a square
root on both
sides what am I going to get I'm going
to get H over
c h over C square of G right
R which is the square root of H bar s g
over c^ 2
no c
s is that dimensionally correct must be
well you took Elric charge no no
electric charge is dimensionless in uh
oh wait a second wait a second wait a
second
um yeah hold on I think uh I think I
lost some Dimensions this is energy uh
this is all right let's let's work let's
do it in terms of energy it's R cubed in
terms of
energy and I want to set that
equal to
e^2 over R but this is not dimensionally
consistent if R is
dimensionless so I need some I need some
H bars and C's in there
um H get charge well I want the charge
to be dimensionless because I happen to
know it's value in dimensionless units
it's about a tenth it's close to one so
uh so we have to put some correct this
has units of energy right if I so so we
have one /
r 1 /
R and if I put an this is not correct
yet it's not correct it's not
dimensionally consistent if I put an H
bar here then this would be momentum H C
if I put a c there it is now
dimensionally
consistent all right c h bar over R has
units of energy and now this electric
charge here is dimensionless and that's
the one which is um uh which is about a
tenth close to
one okay so I made a mistake I thought I
made a mistake I should have uh oh I
erased
it it's lost it's
gone okay
I think it's right now yes okay now
multiply it by R R cubed and we get r
squared up
here now we get a c down C Cube down
here
and remove an H
bar and I get R now is equal to the
square < TK of
g h bar over C cubed I think I like that
better all right what is that
length that's the plunk
length that's the plunk length so the
plunk length is the place where because
of this growth of energy with squeezing
with uh with diminishing the wavelength
because of that the gravitational force
increases and becomes comparable or even
bigger
uh few factors of 10 bigger than the
electromagnetic force at the plunk
length so they also so the
electromagnetic force the weak Force the
strong force and the gravitational force
all grow or all become more or less
comparable somewhere near the plunk
scale this is thought to be deep this is
thought to be something
important if it is as important as it
sounds then the puzzle becomes not why
is the plunk length so small or why is
the plunk Mass so large or why is uh
that 10 to the 19 such a big number it
is why that f is so small small in
natural
units how does it happen that that F
which controls the masses and the energy
scales of all weak electromagnetic all
the ordinary interactions in particular
controls the mass of the Z the W the
quirks the electron why is it so small
that's one
number uh which is you know some 15
orders of magnitude smaller than any
fundamental length scale as far as we
can tell and it's just that one number
which is very small once that one number
is explained why it is so small all the
masses of all the elementary particles
that we know about
follow all the others for all we know
could be up at the plunk mass at the
natural scale they have no reason to be
light they W their masses did not have
to be proportional to this symmetry
breaking scale so that's that's kind of
where we are puzzled about why this F is
so small
now we'll we'll go more deeply into this
next quarter it's not only that it's
small it's also very very finely
tuned
and so if you can somehow calculate F
then you could calculate the other
masses if you could calculate F you
could but you but any any ordinary
calculation of f will give a huge
number why because it'll come out to be
portional to the fundamental scale
unless unless there's some incredible
conspiracy that uh so yeah you can
calculate it in all sorts of theories
that it will come out
huge I'm trying to visualize the plunk
length in terms of the screening
distance when we get so gravitational
physics it's not helpful to think of it
aen okay um yeah that's right it's just
not if you had higher orders de higher
orders in what of uh the in steel p uh
say p to the 6
Etc P what
P
five each of those appear
Le well there are real reasons why not
you wouldn't want to put in five fif
there because that would break the
Symmetry between uh plus five and minus
5 you could put 56 there but um there
are those are Anni and creation
operators those SP that that represents
four h particles coming together
absolutely okay so that's another right
once you know these numbers you can
predict something about the scattering
of higs bosons two higs bosons go to two
higs bons right are are is LIN a polom
in in in all the field variables then
okay so that's pretty restrictive It is
Well it's not it's more restrictive than
you think Beyond 5 to the 4th becomes
what is called non-renormalizable which
is a bad thing to have in a theory so
uh uh we can talk about it why 54 is the
natural of this the Gren is a polom all
field values and there's never never any
exponent four right except when there
is have you left out any
any um any terms like self interaction
or
well self interactions are what goes
into the running of these coupling
constants for example the self
interactions between gluons are what uh
gave you the opposite effect from what
happens in
electrodynamics self- interaction
between flux lines pulls them together
into a into a sort of
cable and the upshot is that the uh
running electric charge changes quite
differently any other thing I thought I
was cross terms between intera between
kinds of intera well there are such
things they come in in higher orders and
you have to calculate them but
fortunately for us all of the coupling
constants are quite
small so the higher order cross terms
are smaller than the uh
things what exactly did you mean when
you said f is finally tuned I didn't I
didn't come to it uh we will discuss it
after now I guess that's that's it's
important since we've talked about
renormalization in groups can you say
something about what the
roral uh not tonight but some
point for more please visit us at
stanford.edu